with just over 14 \ H000 employees and offices in 60 locations.
We are going on behalf of Parliament
and government manage social insurance.
We do this by investigating and deciding on the right to compensation
As well as coordinate rehabilitation efforts to help those who are on sick leave
to get back to working life.
Here is the state value base.
It describes how we who are employed at the Social Insurance Office should relate
ourselves to the power and responsibility we have as employees in the state.
State employees therefore need to have understanding
For citizens, the authority's client.
The activities of an authority
must have support in law or other constitution.
This means that the Social Insurance Agency may not take any action
Or make a decision if we do not support it in laws and regulations.
This is called the principle of legality and encompasses all forms of public
Power of power, including handling in cases at the Swedish Social Insurance Agency.
To understand how the rules should be applied in our business
and impartial in their business.
Objectivity means that unkind circumstances do not
may form the basis for the assessments made and decisions that are made.
People should be able to trust that the handling or outcome of a decision
not affected by the arbitrar of an individual employee,
own perception or personal ideas.
The Social Insurance Office is governed by the Public Authority,
The instruction for the Social Insurance Office
and the government's annual regulatory letter where goals,
Two laws that are good to know are the Administration Act
that form the basis of how one
Managing Authority shall act in relation to individuals
and the Social Security Code, which is the law that regulates
Most compensation paid by the Social Insurance Office.
The government must never control how the authority exercises the laws.
It is the courts that try this.
If there is scope for interpretation on how the legislation is to be applied is
it practice, that is, indicative decisive
not linked to citizenship but what determines if you are insured
In Sweden, whether you live and work here or not.
Some of the insurance can be
Take part in by being registered in Sweden.
They are called settlement -based benefits.
Other Insurance assumes that you work or have
Worked in Sweden.
These are the work -based benefits.
In addition to being insured in Sweden, one also needs to meet the conditions in question
for the compensation you applied for.
It can be work -oriented, medical
Or of a leisure nature and it should have a positive impact on the person.
One can also receive activity compensation for extended schooling
If the disability you have makes you need longer
to complete their schooling in elementary school or high school.
Sickness benefit is granted so far and may be relevant
If you will not be able to work more or just be able to work part -time.
Sickness compensation can be granted from the age of 30
Until you can take out old -age pension.
Each year is granted approximately 5300
persons sickness benefit.
When the Swedish Social Insurance Agency assesses whether the individual is entitled to activity compensation
or sickness compensation we look at the ability to work
in relation to the entire labor market, also protected employment.
This applies to everyone under 61 years.
For those over 61 years there is a special rule that means that work ability
only tested against such work as the person has experience with
and worked with over the past 15 years.